谎言的代价是什么
What is the cost of lies?
并不是它会被错当成真相
It's not that we'll mistake them for the truth.
真正的危险是  如果我们听了太多谎言
The real danger is that if we hear enough lies,
会再无法分辨出真相
then we no longer recognize the truth at all.
到时我们要怎么办
What can we do then?
只能抛弃追寻真相的希望
What else is left but to abandon even the hope of truth
而满足于编造的故事
and content ourselves instead with stories?
在这些故事里  我们不关心英雄是谁
In these stories, it doesn't matter who the heroes are.
只想知道  该责怪谁
All we want to know is: who is to blame?
莫斯科
1988年4月26日
在这则故事里  安纳托利·迪亚特洛夫被怪罪
In this story, it was Anatoly Dyatlov.
他是最佳选择
He was the best choice.
他是个自大讨厌的人
An arrogant, unpleasant man,
他是那晚的负责人  是他下了令
he ran the room that night, he gave the orders...
而且他没有朋友
and no friends.
至少  没有身居高位的朋友
Or, at least, not important ones.
现在  迪亚特洛夫被判在劳改营
And now Dyatlov will spend the next ten years
服刑十年
in a prison labor camp.
当然了  这个刑罚并不公平
Of course, that sentence is doubly unfair.
还有比他罪行更深重的人
There were far greater criminals than him at work.
而就迪亚特洛夫的确犯的罪而言
And as for what Dyatlov did do,
他也不该被判服刑
the man doesn't deserve prison.
他该被判死刑
He deserves death.
但他被判了十年  罪名是"管理不善罪"
But instead, ten years for "criminal mismanagement."
那什么意思啊
What does that mean?
没人知道  也无所谓
No one knows. It doesn't matter.
重要的是  对于他们来说
What does matter is that, to them,
正义已得伸张
justice was done.
因为你瞧  对于他们
Because, you see, to them
正义的世界  是正常的
a just world is a sane world.
但切尔诺贝利事件毫无正常可言
There was nothing sane about Chernobyl.
那里发生的事  后来发生的事
What happened there, what happened after,
甚至是我们做的补救  那一切
even the good we did, all of it...
全部都...是疯狂的
all of it... madness.
我已说出了我知道的一切
Well, I've given you everything I know.
他们当然会否认
They'll deny it, of course.
一向如此
They always do.
我知道你会尽力而为
I know you'll try your best.
原创翻译  双语字幕
最新连载海外影视剧下载
请登陆 www.YYeTs.com
仅供交流学习  禁止商用盈利
翻译   草草  哈里不是波特  tong大梨
翻译     elingbow  白夜君  DerbyNinja
翻译     放开那个方丈  小胖橘子  苏葵
顾问     elingbow
校对     草草  苏葵
时间轴     荞麦麦  Caroline
后期     8T  拉图
总监     苏葵
切尔诺贝利
第一集
苏联乌克兰  普里皮亚季
两年零一分钟前
柳德米拉
Lyudmilla?
迪亚特洛夫同志  迪亚特洛夫同志
Comrade Dyatlov! Comrade Dyatlov!
发生了什么
What just happened?
我不知道
I don't know.
汽轮机大厅着火了
There's a fire in the turbine hall.
汽轮机大厅
The turbine hall.
控制系统水箱  氢气
The control system tank. Hydrogen.
你和托普特诺夫  你俩白痴把水箱炸了
You and Toptunov, you morons blew the tank!
-不是的  -现在是紧急情况
- No, that's not-- - This is an emergency.
所有人保持冷静  我们首先要...
Everyone stay calm. Our first priority is--
-爆炸了  -我们知道了
- It's exploded! - We know.
阿基莫夫  在冷却反应堆芯了吧
Akimov, are we cooling the reactor core?
已关闭反应堆  但控制棒仍在运行
We shut it down, but the control rods are still active.
没有完全插入  我已切断离合了
They're not all the way in, I disengaged the clutch.
试试用备用控制台切断伺服系统
Try and disconnect the servos from the standby console.
你俩  去启动备用泵
You two, get the backup pumps running.
我们需要水流过堆芯
We need water moving through the core.
-那才是最重要的  -堆芯没了
- That is all that matters. - There is no core.
爆炸了  堆芯爆炸了
It exploded, the core exploded.
他吓傻了  把他带出去
He's in shock. Get him out of here.
盖子飞了
The lid is off!
石墨砌体烧起来了  我看见的
The stack is burning. I saw it.
压力管式石墨慢化沸水核反应堆
你脑子乱了  RBMK反应堆的堆芯不可能爆炸
You're confused. RBMK reactor cores don't explode.
-阿基莫夫...  -萨沙
- Akimov... - Sasha.
别担心  我们的操作没有问题
Don't worry, we did everything right.
是...发生了什么奇怪的事
Something... something strange has happened.
-你尝到金属味儿了吗  -阿基莫夫
- Do you taste metal? - Akimov!
佩罗沃钦科同志
Comrade Perevozchenko,
你所说的在物理上是不可能的
what you're saying is physically impossible.
堆芯不会爆炸  只可能是水箱爆炸
The core can't explode. It has to be the tank.
我们在耽误时间  快行动
We're wasting time. Let's go.
把氢从发电机中排出去  泵水到堆芯里
Get the hydrogen out of the generators and pump water into the core.
-那火怎么办呢  -叫消防队来
- What about the fire? - Call the fire brigade.
喂  是军队第二消防站吗
是
事故什么情况
第三和第四厂房之间的主建筑发生爆炸
那边有人吗
有
把领导们都叫起来  给他们打电话
我已经给我的领导打了电话
把他们全叫醒  把整个领导住宅楼都叫醒
消防部
伊万科夫吗
什么事
你们被派去普里皮亚季
喂
我能听到你
那边核电站的第三和第四厂房屋顶着火了
你今晚不值班啊
You're not on call tonight.
他们调集了所有人  军事和民用消防局
They're bringing everybody in, military and civil.
普里皮亚季  玻列斯科  基辅
Pripyat, Polesskoe, Kiev.
这次火情很严重
This is a big one.
但看起来不对劲  那颜色
But it doesn't look right, the color.
普拉维克说他们可能打开了泛光灯什么的
Pravik says he thinks they're shining floodlights or something.
那如果有什么化学物质呢
And what if there are chemicals?
化学物质
Chemicals?
问题出在屋顶
The problem's the roof.
上面铺着沥青  所以会烧上一晚上
It's covered in tar, so it's gonna burn all night,
而且会臭得要命  仅此而已
and it'll stink like hell. That's it.
这就是最糟的了
That's the worst of it.
接着睡觉吧
Go back to bed.
凌晨1点25分
-是打仗了吗  -放射性剂量仪在哪
- Is it war? - Where's the dosimeter?
在这...这
Here... Here.
他们在轰炸吗
Are they bombing?
这他妈怎么回事  3.6伦琴
What the fuck is this? It's 3.6 roentgen.
那是仪表上限  精度高的锁在保险柜里
That's as high as it goes. The good one's locked in a safe.
我没有钥匙
I don't have a key.
瓦列拉...你的脸
Valera... your face.
起来
Come on.
我去循环泵室找霍登楚克
I'm going to find Khodemchuk in the pump room.
你...留在这
You... here.
去找沙申诺克  他在604室  去吧
Get Shashenok. He's in 604. Go.
我们得让大家都出去
We need to get everyone out!
该死
Shit.
我们要去反应堆大厅
We need to get to the reactor hall.
-电梯坏了  -上两层然后穿过去
- The lift's destroyed. - Up two flights and across.
-好  -你们去那干什么
- Right. - Why are you going there?
你看见霍登楚克了吗
Have you seen Khodemchuk?
-没有  维克多在哪  -还在循环泵室
- No. Where's Viktor? - Still in the pump room.
在这待着  我一会回来
Stay here. I'll come back.
维克多
Viktor!
Viktor.
维克多
维克多  我带你出去
Viktor. I'm gonna get you out of here.
你能站起来吗
Can you stand?
霍登楚克
Khodemchuk...
在哪
Where?
去找霍登楚克
Get Khodemchuk.
我用另一个控制面板插入了控制棒
I dropped the control rods from the other panel.
-它们还在外头呢  -什么
- They're still up. - What?
只插入了三分之一  我也不知道为什么
They're still only a third of the way in, I don't know why.
我派了实习生下去
I already sent the trainees
到反应堆大厅手动插入控制棒
down to the reactor hall to lower them by hand.
循环泵那边呢
What about the pumps?
联系不上霍登楚克
I can't get through to Khodemchuk.
电话坏了
The lines are down.
去他妈的电话  去他妈的霍登楚克
Fuck the phones and fuck Khodemchuk.
-循环泵开了吗  -斯托利楚克
- Are the pumps on or not? - Stolyarchuk?
我的控制面板失效了
My control panel's not working.
我试着联系电工了
I tried calling for the electricians.
我不关心什么面板
I don't give a shit about the panel!
我需要给反应堆芯通水
I need water in my reactor core!
到下面去  确保循环泵都开了
Get down there and make sure those pumps are on.
马上
Now!
现在放射量有多少
What does the dosimeter say?
3.6伦琴  但那是仪表上限
3.6 roentgen, but that's as high as the meter--
3.6  不好也不坏
3.6-- not great, not terrible.
我们的操作没有问题
We did everything right.
凌晨1点30分
你  把这都接上
You, connect those hooks!
启动水泵
Get the pumps going!
是  这边
Yeah, over here!
我们从下往上灭火  快点
We're working bottom to top. Go in fast.
瓦西里
Vasily...
-瓦西里  这是什么  -不知道  米沙
- Hey, Vasily, what's this? - I don't know, Misha.
别瞎摆弄了  把这些都接上  快来
Don't fuck around with it. Hook these up, come on.
你尝到金属味儿了吗
Do you taste metal?
-嗯  那是什么  -我不知道
- Yeah, what is that? - I don't know.
阀门  米沙  开阀门  快
The valves, Misha! The valves, let's go!
开阀门  快点
The valves! Come on!
你们要做什么
What do you need?
我们要到反应堆大厅去
We need to get into the reactor hall
插入控制棒  但是门卡住了
to lower the control rods, but the door is jammed.
控制棒应该已经没有了
I don't think there are control rods.
堆芯也没了
I don't think there's a core.
不  你...你错了
No, you're-- you're mistaken.
阿基莫夫说的
Akimov said.
咱们走
Let's go.
不
No!
伊格纳滕科  把他的水管捡起来
Ignatenko, get on his hose!
没事  呼吸
It's all right. Breathe.
米沙
Misha.
好了  没事  放松  米沙
All right, all right. Easy, Misha.
你确定吗
Are you sure?
阿基莫夫
Akimov...
让开
Move.
快点  进去
Come on, go!
我们走
Let's go!
柳德米拉  你和我们一起去吗
Lyudmilla! Do you want to come with us?
去哪儿
Come where?
我们要到铁路桥上  那边看得更清楚
We're going to the railroad bridge to get a better look.
反正警报声这么大  谁都睡不着
It's not like anyone can sleep with all the sirens.
我觉得你们不应该去  可能有危险
I don't think you should go. It could be dangerous.
哪有什么危险  只是火灾而已
What do you mean dangerous? It's a fire.
离得那么远
It's over there, we're over here.
-米哈伊尔  -怎么了
- Mikhail. - What?
抱歉
Oh, sorry.
-瓦西里去了  -是的
- Is Vasily...? - Yeah.
他说情况很糟糕吗
Did he say it was bad?
不  不  他说只是楼顶着火了
No. No, he said it was just the roof.
他从来都没有受过伤
Well, he's never gotten hurt before.
他们都没有过
None of the boys have.
他会没事的
He'll be fine.
去休息会儿吧
Get some rest.
水箱足够大
The tank, it's big enough.
这样的爆炸
This kind of explosion,
标高71米处的控制水箱有100立方米
the control tank on 71, it's 100 cubic meters.
是110
One hundred and ten.
110  绝对有这种威力
Hundred and ten. It could do this, definitely.
没了
It's gone.
我看到里面了
I looked right into it.
我看到堆芯了
I looked into the core.
你到底有没有插入控制棒
Did you lower the control rods or not?
带他去医务室
Take him to the infirmary.
托普特诺夫  带他去
Toptunov, take him!
-科锥亚弗斯塔夫在哪儿  -他摔倒了
- Where's Kudryavstev? - He fell.
-我需要医生  有人吗  -他脑子不清楚了
- I need a medic! Anyone! - He's delusional.
-他的脸  -冷凝器管道断裂
- His face... - Ruptured condenser lines.
给水受到轻度污染
The feedwater is mildly contaminated.
他会没事的  这还不是最糟的
He'll be fine. I've seen worse.
还有和外面接通的电话线路吗
Do we still have a phone line to the outside?
阿基莫夫
Akimov?
叫白班的人来
Call in the day shift.
-但如果  -我们必须持续向堆芯注水
- But if the-- - We have to keep water flowing into the core.
我们需要电工  机械师  需要人手
We need electricians, mechanics, we need bodies.
还要我说几遍
How many times do I have to say it?
我要去行政楼
I'm going to the Administration Building now
联系布卡诺夫和福明
to call Bryukhanov and Fomin.
他们会让我提交详细报告
They're gonna want a full report.
我不知道我能不能让你好过些
Now, I don't know if I can make things better for you,
但我绝对能让你不好过
but I can certainly make them worse.
叫白班的人来  阿基莫夫同志
Call in the day shift, Comrade Akimov.
好  迪亚特洛夫同志
Yes, Comrade Dyatlov.
凌晨1点50分
你情况很好
You're doing fine.
把她抬起来
Raise her up.
那个  可能还有一小时
That one, maybe an hour.
这个  要等到早上了
This one, not until morning.
-楼下怎么样  医生  -很安静
- How's it downstairs, doctor? - Quiet.
一向如此
Always is.
这个时候只有婴儿的声音
Nothing at this hour but babies.
知道吗  我曾经连续两天没有睡觉
You know, I once went two days without sleep?
十个女人同时分娩
Ten women went into labor at the same time.
-我跟你说过这个故事吗  -说过
- Did I ever tell you that story? - Yes.
我这里暂时不需要你
Well, I won't need you in here for a while.
你可以去休息室休息一下
If you want, get some rest in the break room.
他们还没从火灾现场送来伤员
They haven't brought anyone in from the fire.
-什么火灾  -核电站火灾
- What fire? - The power plant.
那说明火势一定不大
Then it mustn't be too bad.
我们有碘吗
Do we stock iodine?
-什么  -碘
- Hmm? - Iodine.
-你是说消毒剂吗  -不  是片剂
- You mean disinfectant? - No, pills.
医院有碘片吗
Does the hospital stock iodine pills?
碘片  我们为什么会有碘片
Iodine pills? Why would we have iodine pills?
喂
Hello?
还有谁知道这件事
Who else knows this?
你打给福明了吗
Have you called Fomin?
我当然希望你打给他
Of course I want you to call him.
如果我醒了  他也得醒
If I'm up, he's up.
不管是什么原因  最重要的是
Whatever the cause, the important thing is
你和我都没...
that neither you nor I--
凌晨2点30分
我猜安全测试失败了
I take it the safety test was a failure?
-情况已经被我们控制住了  -控制住了
- We have the situation under control. - Under control?
-看起来可不像控制住了  -闭嘴  福明
- It doesn't look like it's under control. - Shut up, Fomin.
我得把这件事告诉中央委员会
I have to tell the Central Committee about this.
你们知道吗
Do you realize that?
我得打电话告诉马瑞因
I have to get on the phone and tell Maryin,
或更甚  告诉弗罗里谢夫
or God forbid Frolyshev,
我的核电站着火了
that my power plant is on fire.
没人能因此怪罪你  布卡诺夫厂长
No one can blame you for this, Director Bryukhanov.
当然没人能因此怪罪我
Of course no one can blame me for this.
我怎么会有责任呢  我当时在睡觉
How can I be responsible? I was sleeping.
告诉我发生了什么  快点的
Tell me what happened, quickly.
我们按福明总工程师批准的方案运行了测试
We ran the test exactly as Chief Engineer Fomin approved.
然后值班长阿基莫夫和工程师托普特诺夫
Unit Shift Chief Akimov and Engineer Toptunov
遇到了一个技术困难
encountered technical difficulties
导致氢在控制系统水箱中聚集
leading to an accumulation of hydrogen in the control system tank.
然后它被点燃了
It regrettably ignited,
破坏了工厂  导致屋顶起火
damaging the plant, setting the roof on fire.
那个水箱很大
The tank is quite large.
这是唯一合理的解释
It's the only logical explanation.
当然  副总工程师迪亚特洛夫
Of course, Deputy Chief Engineer Dyatlov
是测试的直接监督人
was directly supervising the test,
所以他知道得最清楚
so he would know best.
一个充满氢气的水箱  火灾
A hydrogen tank, fire...
-反应堆呢  -我们正在采取措施
- Reactor? - We're taking measures to ensure
确保有稳定的水流流过堆芯
a steady flow of water through the core.
-辐射情况呢  -在这里当然没有
- What about radiation? - Obviously, down here it's nothing.
但是在反应堆厂房里  有人告诉我是
But in the reactor building, I'm being told
每小时3.6伦琴
3.6 roentgen per hour.
不太妙  但也不太糟
Well, that's not great, but it's not horrifying.
完全不
Not at all.
是给水的辐射咯
From the feedwater, I assume?
我们得限制换班时间到
We'll have to limit shifts
每六小时一换  但除此之外...
to six hours at a time, but otherwise...
剂量测定员要定期检查
The dosimetrists should be checking regularly.
让他们用保险柜里的高精度仪表
Have them use the good meter from the safe.
好吧  我去打给马瑞因
Right. I'll call Maryin.
去叫醒当地的执行委员会
Have them wake up the local executive committee.
上头随时会有命令
There'll be orders coming down.
-给  -不用
- Here. - No.
你确定吗  好吧
You sure? Okay.
你觉得颜色是哪儿来的
What do you think makes the colors?
-肯定是燃料  -"肯定是燃料"
- It's the fuel for sure. - "Oh. It's the fuel for sure"?
你知道什么  你在火车站拖地
What do you know about it? You clean floors at a train station.
我朋友尤里在核电站工作
My friend, Yuri, works at the power plant.
他说那里不点火
He says it runs cold.
没有气体  没有火  只有原子
No gas, no fire. Just atoms.
尤里说唯一不能做的事就是靠近燃料
Yuri says the only thing is, you can't walk right up to the fuel.
一旦靠近
If you do,
就得连续四个小时每小时喝一杯伏特加
a glass of vodka an hour for four hours.
尤里不是水管工吗
Isn't Yuri a plumber?
核电站的水管工  没错
At the nuclear power plant, yeah.
可真美啊
It is beautiful.
没错
Yeah.
你有烟吗
Do you have a cigarette?
需要帮忙吗
Do you need help?
完蛋了
It's over.
我们在外面已束手无策了
We've done all we can from the perimeter.
我们得上屋顶
We need to start making our way to the roof.
瓦西里  得把火扑灭
Vasily! You've gotta put it out.
够了  同志们  我们往前走
That's enough, comrades. We're pushing ahead.
来吧  各位
Come on, boys.
瓦西里  就在前面  直走
Vasily, it's just past, straight up.
一直上去  往里走
All the way up, all the way in.
快点
Come on!
现在进入
Yeah. Going in now.
凌晨3点30分
那辅助装置呢
What about the auxiliary?
泵全毁了  电子设备也没了
The pumps are gone, electrical's gone.
堆芯呢
The core?
我没进去  我也不会进去的
I didn't go in there, and I won't.
我想是时候面对...
I think it's time we faced--
不  我们必须要把水注入堆芯里
No, we have to get water into the core.
否则堆芯会熔毁的
Otherwise, there'll be a meltdown.
我们必须把阀门打开
We have to open the valves.
-萨沙  -那你想怎么做  鲍里斯
- Sasha... - What do you want, Boris?
如果真是这样  我们死定了
If it's true, then we're dead,
上百万人都死定了
a million people are dead.
你想听这话吗
Is that what you need to hear?
我们必须把阀门打开
We have to open the valves.
-手动打开  -手动打开
- By hand. - By hand?
阀门的数量  转动阀门的时间
You know, the number of valves, the amount of time to turn them,
那可要在里面待上几个小时
you're talking about hours in there!
-那就帮帮我们吧  -帮你们做什么
- Then help us. - Help you do what?
把水抽进沟里吗  那里什么都没有了
Pump water into a ditch? There's nothing there!
列尼德  我求你了
Leonid, I'm begging you.
我们不在的时候  看着点仪表板
Watch the panel while we're gone.
已经坏了
It's not working.
看着就是了
Just watch it.
我猜这就是他们这么早召集我们的原因
I guess we know why they called us in early.
有人说发生了什么事吗
Is anyone saying what happened?
他们之前在对汽轮机进行安全测试
They were running the safety test on the turbines,
结果炸毁了控制系统水箱
blew the control system tank.
我也不明白
It doesn't make sense to me either.
会不会是有人搞破坏
What about sabotage?
或是炸弹
A bomb?
斯特尼考夫  布卡诺夫要我们用精度高的剂量计
Sitnikov! Bryukhanov wants us to use the good dosimeter,
但剂量计在保险箱里  我们找不到钥匙
but it's in the safe, and we can't find the key.
在2号厂房里  难道还没...
It's in Building 2. Hasn't--?
跟我来
Follow me.
凌晨5点20分
先生们  欢迎
Gentlemen, welcome.
请  随便坐吧  很多座位
Please, uh, find a seat. Plenty of room.
抱歉这么晚把你们叫过来
I apologize for the lateness of the hour.
放心  这个地方很安全
Rest assured, we are all very safe down here.
这个庇护所
We built this shelter
是建来抵挡美国核攻击的
to withstand a nuclear attack by the Americans,
所以我觉得我们应该没事
so I think we'll be fine.
如你们所见  刚发生了一次事故
As you can see, we have experienced an accident.
一个大型控制水箱出现故障
A large control tank malfunctioned,
导致4号反应堆厂房发生损坏  并引发火灾
damaging reactor Building 4 and starting a fire.
我立即就上报马瑞因副书记了
Now, I have spoken directly to Deputy Secretary Maryin.
马瑞因上报了弗罗里谢夫副局长
Maryin spoke to Deputy Chief Frolyshev,
弗罗里谢夫上报了中央委员会委员多尔基
Frolyshev to Central Committee member Dolgikh,
多尔基上报了戈尔巴乔夫总书记
and Dolgikh to General Secretary Gorbachev.
那么
Now...
因为中央委员会极其尊重
Because the Central Committee has the greatest respect
普里皮亚季执行委员会
for the work of the Pripyat Executive Committee,
他们要求我如实对你们汇报情况  所以
they have asked me to brief you on matters as they stand, so...
首先事故已经得到控制
First, the accident... is well under control.
其次  因为苏联在核工业方面的工作
And second, because the efforts of the Soviet nuclear industry
属于国家机密
are considered key state secrets,
因此我们要确保这起事故
it is important that we ensure that
不产生任何负面影响
this incident has no adverse consequences.
为避免恐慌  中央委员会已下令
Now, to prevent a panic, the Central Committee have ordered
向普里皮亚季派遣一支宪兵队
a detachment of military police to Pripyat.
特遣队有多大规模
How large of a detachment?
两千到四千人
Between two and four thousand men.
到底发生了什么  会有多危险
What's really going on here? How dangerous is this?
有轻微的辐射  但只在工厂范围内
There's mild radiation, but it's limited to the plant itself.
-不  不对  -你说什么
- No, it isn't. - Excuse me?
你们也看到了外面有人在呕吐
You saw men outside vomiting.
你们也看到了有人被烧伤
You saw men with burns.
辐射情况比他们说的要严重得多
There's more radiation than they're saying.
这里有我们的妻子  我们的孩子
We have wives here, we have children.
我觉得我们应该安排全镇撤离
I say we evacuate the town.
先生们
Gentlemen--
拜托  拜托  我妻子也在这儿
Please, please. My wife is here.
如果普里皮亚季不安全
Do you think I would keep her in Pripyat
我还会把她留在这吗
if it wasn't safe?
布卡诺夫  空气都在发光
Bryukhanov, the air is glowing.
这是切伦科夫效应  是正常现象
The Cherenkov effect. Completely normal phenomenon.
粒子在媒质中传播速度超过媒质中光速时产生的辐射效应
只要有一点辐射都会发生这种现象
It can happen with minimal radiation.
我好奇你们中有多少人知道这个地方的名字
I wonder how many of you know the name of this place.
当然  我们都叫它"切尔诺贝利"
We all call it "Chernobyl," of course.
但它的真名是什么呢
What is its real name?
弗拉基米尔·伊里奇·列宁核电站
The Vladimir I. Lenin Nuclear Power Station.
对
Exactly.
弗拉基米尔·伊里奇·列宁
Vladimir I. Lenin.
今晚他会为你们感到十分自豪的
And how proud he would be of you all tonight.
尤其是你  年轻人
Especially you, young man,
以及你们对人民的关切
and the passion you have for the people.
难道这不是成立国家政府唯一目的吗
For is that not the sole purpose of the apparatus of the State?
但有时候  我们会忘记
Sometimes, we forget.
有时候  我们沦为恐惧的牺牲品
Sometimes, we fall prey to fear.
但我们对苏联社会主义的信仰
But our faith in Soviet socialism
终将得到回报
will always be rewarded.
政府告诉我们这里的情况并不危险
Now, the State tells us the situation here is not dangerous.
同志们  要有信心
Have faith, comrades.
政府告诉我们要避免恐慌
The State tells us it wants to prevent a panic.
听好了
Listen well.
没错  当人们看到警察  他们会害怕
It's true, when the people see the police, they will be afraid.
但根据我的经验
But it is my experience
当人们提出一些
that when the people ask questions
对自己不利的问题时
that are not in their own best interest,
应该有人告诉他们
they should simply be told
把心思放在工作上
to keep their minds on their labor
将国家的问题留给国家解决
and leave matters of the State to the State.
我们封锁城市
We seal off the city.
谁都不许离开
No one leaves.
切断电话线
And cut the phone lines.
以防消息的误传
Contain the spread of misinformation.
我们需要防止人民
That is how we keep the people
破坏自己的劳动成果
from undermining the fruits of their own labor.
是的  同志们
Yes, comrades...
我们都将因今晚的所作所为受到奖赏
we will all be rewarded for what we do here tonight.
这正是我们发光发热的时刻
This is our moment to shine.
谢谢大家
Thank you.
斯特尼考夫同志来见总工程师
Comrade Sitnikov to see the Chief Engineer.
怎么样
Well?
我派剂量测定员进入反应堆厂房
I sent my dosimetrists into the reactor building.
保险箱中那个大型的剂量计
The large dosimeter from the safe,
最大测量值为一千伦琴的那个
the one with the 1,000-roentgen capacity--
测量读数是多少
What was the number?
没有读数
There was none.
剂量计一开启就烧坏了
The meter burned out the second it was turned on.
-不出所料  -瞧  这就是莫斯科干的事
- It's typical. - See? This is what Moscow does.
给我们送来垃圾设备  还问我们哪里出了错
Sends us shit equipment, then wonders why things go wrong.
我们从军事消防局找到了
We found another dosimeter
另一个剂量计
from the military fire department.
它最大测量值只有二百伦琴
It only goes to 200 roentgen,
但总比小那个的强
but it's better than the small ones.
怎么样
And?
它爆表了
It maxed out.
二百伦琴
Two hundred roentgen.
你在耍什么花招
What game are you playing?
不  我让他
No, I--I-- I asked him,
他测了好几次  他是我最好的测量员了
he took multiple measurements, he's my best man.
也是个故障剂量计  你在浪费我们的时间
It's another faulty meter. You're wasting our time.
我检测了控制水箱附近的读数
I checked the meter against the control.
你怎么回事  你怎么能从爆炸后的水箱
What's wrong with you? How'd you get that number
流出的给水中测到这种读数
from feedwater leaking from a blown tank?
-是不可能  -那你在说些什么玩意
- You don't. - Then what the fuck are you talking about?
我
I, um...
我围着4号厂房的外围走了一圈
I walked around the exterior of Building 4.
我认为地上的碎砖瓦中有石墨
I think there's graphite on the ground in the rubble.
你没有看到石墨
You didn't see graphite.
-我看到了  -你没有
- I did. - You didn't.
你没看到  因为根本没有
You didn't! Because it's not there!
什么
What?
你的意思是堆芯  怎么了
Are you suggesting the core... what?
爆炸了吗
Exploded?
是的
Yes.
斯特尼考夫
Sitnikov.
你是一个核工程师  我也是
You're a nuclear engineer, so am I.
给我解释下RBMK型反应堆的堆芯怎么会爆炸
Please tell me how an RBMK reactor core explodes.
不是熔毁  是爆炸
Not a meltdown, an explosion.
我很乐意听听
I'd love to know.
我解释不了
I can't.
你是蠢货吗
Are you stupid?
-不是  -那你怎么解释不了
- No. - Then why can't you?
我...
I...
我不明白它为什么会爆炸
I don't see how it could explode.
-但它的确爆炸了  -够了
- But it did. - Enough!
我去通风厂房楼顶
I'll go up to the vent block roof.
从那可以直接看到4号厂房
From there you can look right down into reactor Building 4.
我要亲眼看看
I'll see it with my own... my own eyes.
对不起
I apologize.
警卫  警卫
Guards! Guards!
带他去医生那里或去医院  给他必要的治疗
Get him to the medic or the hospital! Whatever he needs!
是给水  他整晚都在那周围
It's the feedwater. Been around it all night.
那你去
You go then.
什么
What?
-去通风厂房楼顶  汇报你看到的东西  -不
- Go to the vent block roof and report back what you see. - No.
-不  我不去  -你当然要去
- No, I won't do that. - Of course you will.
你不会有事的  放心
You'll be fine. You'll see.
去吧
Come on.
好吧
Okay.
开始吧
Let's begin.
列尼德
Leonid.
全部打开  明白吗
It's all the way, okay?
全部打开
All the way open.
对不起
I'm sorry.
没什么好对不起的
There's nothing to be sorry for.
我说了  我们的操作没有问题
I told you, we did nothing wrong.
但肯定有问题
But we did.
喂
Hello?
-瓦列利·列加索夫吗  -是我
- Valery Legasov? - Yes.
你是库尔恰托夫原子能研究所研究所的
You are the Legasov who is the First Deputy Director
第一副所长列加索夫
of the Kurchatov Institute of Atomic Energy?
-是我  你是...  -我是鲍里斯·谢比纳
- I am. Who am I--? - This is Boris Shcherbina,
部长理事会的副主席
Deputy Chairman of the Council of Ministers
及燃料与能源局局长
and head of the Bureau for Fuel and Energy.
切尔诺贝利核电站发生了一起事故
There's been an accident at the Chernobyl Nuclear Power Plant.
有多严重
How bad is it?
不严重  无需担忧  起火了
No. No need to panic. There was a fire.
大部分火势已被扑灭  系统控制水箱爆炸了
It's mostly put out. The system control tank exploded.
控制系统水箱  那堆芯呢
Control system tank. And the core?
我们已下令持续供水冷却
We've ordered them to continuously pump water.
我明白了  有污染吗
Yes, I see. Any contamination?
轻度污染  核电站厂长布卡诺夫说
It's mild. The plant manager, Bryukhanov, is reporting
每小时3.6伦琴
3.6 roentgen per hour.
这还挺严重  你们应该撤离
That's actually significant. You should evacuate the sur--
你是RBMK反应堆的专家  对吗
You're an expert on RBMK reactors, correct?
-对  我研究过  -米哈伊尔·戈尔巴乔夫总书记
- Yes, I've studied-- - General Secretary Gorbachev has appointed
设立了一个委员会处理事故  你也是其中一员
a committee to manage the accident. You're on it.
今天下午两点集合
We'll convene at two this afternoon.
这么晚  不好意思  但你不觉得
That late? Forgive me, but don't you think
鉴于辐射的强度  应该...
given the amount of radiation that it would be--
列加索夫  你在委员会的职责是回答
Legasov, you're on this committee to answer direct questions
任何与RBMK反应堆有关的问题
about the function of an RBMK reactor
倘若有人提问的话  仅此而已
if they should happen to arise. Nothing else.
绝非参与决策制定  你明白了吗
Certainly not policy. Do you understand?
当然  我无意...
Yes, of course. I didn't mean to-- -
我很高兴地汇报
I'm pleased to report
切尔诺贝利的情况已稳定了下来
that the situation in Chernobyl is stable.
就辐射而言
In terms of radiation,
我被告知辐射量相当于一次胸透
I'm told it's the equivalent of a chest X-ray.
不
No!
大火释放的辐射量近乎是
The fire is giving off nearly twice the radiation
广岛原子弹的两倍
released by the bomb in Hiroshima.
它会一直燃烧  散布毒素
It will burn and spread its poison
直到杀死整片大陆
until the entire continent is dead.
《切尔诺贝利》
剧情预告
告诉士兵们
Tell our soldiers,
"务必快速行动
"You will need to move quickly,
万分小心
and you will need to move carefully.
这是你们人生中最重要的90秒
These are the most important 90 seconds of your lives.
祝你们长寿健康"
I wish you good health and long life."
为苏联服务
I serve the Soviet Union.
国家的官方立场是
The official position of the state
苏联是不会发生
is that a global nuclear catastrophe
全球性灾难事故的
is not possible in the Soviet Union.
切尔诺贝利